{"tossups": [{"question": "This man appointed Gennadius Scholarius as head for Orthodox Christians in his empire. 800 people were supposedly martyred in Otranto after an invasion by this ruler\u2019s forces, who also captured Albania after Skanderbeg died. This ruler\u2019s advance on Hungary was delayed after John Hunyadi\u2019s successful resistance at Belgrade. This ruler\u2019s greatest success began with construction of the Rumeli Hisari, forcing Constantine XI to call for help. Upon capturing a capital, this sultan proclaimed himself \u201cCaesar\u201d of Rome. For the point, name this Ottoman ruler who in 1453 took Constantinople.", "answer": "Fatih Sultan<b> Mehmed II</b> the Conquerer (prompt on<b> Mehmed</b> alone, accept<b> Mehmed the Conquerer</b>) (2) This empire traced its roots to Andragoras\u2019 rebellion and subsequent invasions by the Parni tribe. Queen Musa co-ruled this empire after murdering her spouse Phraates IV. The houses of Karen and Suren were thought to have originated in this empire. After invading Armenia, Osroes I was temporarily deposed as ruler of this empire as retaliation by Trajan. Augustus bargained with this empire for the return of eagle standards captured by this empire after Crassus\u2019 defeat at Carrhae. For the point, name this empire ruled by the Arsacid dynasty and succeeded by the Sassanids. ANSWER:<b> Parthia</b>n Empire (or<b> Parthian</b>s or<b> Arsacid</b> Empire before mention, prompt on \u201cPersia(n)\u201d)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Opothleyahola led a band of this tribe to Fort Row, Kansas on the Trail of Blood on Ice. In response to an ambush at Burnt Corn Creek, William Weatherford and Peter McQueen led this tribe in an attack on Fort Mims. The Treaty of Fort Jackson forced this tribe\u2019s surrender shortly after their defeat at Horseshoe Bend. For the point, name this tribe, whose Red Stick faction fought a namesake war against Andrew Jackson as part of the larger War of 1812.", "answer": "<b> Creek</b> Indians (or<b> Muscogee</b> Indians) (do not accept \u201cRed Stick\u201d or \u201cLower Creeks\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader constructed the \u201cVersailles of the Jungle\u201d at Gbadolite and frequently traveled to Paris on shopping trips via Concorde. This leader changed both his own name and that of his country in his decolonization program, Authenticit\u00b4e. The MPR was the only legal party during this leader\u2019s rule, which was overthrown by AFDL rebels led by Laurent-D\u00b4esir\u00b4e Kabila. This leader seized power from Joseph Kasa-Vubu in a coup and arranged the assassination of Patrice Lumumba. For the point, name this former president who renamed the Democratic Republic of the Congo to Zaire.", "answer": "<b> Mobutu</b> Sese Seko (Accept Joseph-D\u00b4esir\u00b4e<b> Mobutu</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "George Bernard Shaw satirized a scandal involving a company named for this man in his play<em> The</em> <em>Music Cure</em>. Jack Phillips and Harold Bride worked for a company named for this man and operated one of this man\u2019s inventions on the<em> Titanic</em>. This man founded a company that included the New Street Works factory which broadcasted Nellie Melba. This man\u2019s first transmission was, \u201cAre you ready,\u201d and at Toynbee Hall, he gave the lecture, \u201cTelegraphy without Wires.\u201d For the point, name this Italian who won a Nobel Prize for his work on developing the radio.", "answer": "Guglielmo<b> Marconi</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In July 2003, Marc and Ronald Fisher were injured in one of these events outside Mulcahy Stadium in Anchorage, delaying an Alaska Baseball League game. Four days after giving up three runs in less than two innings in the 2006 ALDS, Cory Lidle died in one of these events. In the offseason after collecting his 3,000th career hit, Roberto Clemente died in one of these events while working to bring aid to Nicaragua. Catcher Thurman Munson died during the 1979 season in, for the point, what type of tragedy, after which the Yankees sued Cessna?", "answer": "<b> plane crash</b> (accept equivalent descriptions; prompt on partial answers, like \u201caccident\u201d or\u201ccrash\u201d)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Eleanor Roosevelt made sure one of this organization\u2019s projects protected the only town named for Martha Washington. Harry Truman rallied support during negotiations for one of this organization\u2019s projects by stating, \u201cI want aluminum, I don\u2019t care if I get if from Alcoa or Al Capone\u201d, leading to the Fontana agreement. This organization provided much of the electricity needed for uranium enrichment at Oak Ridge. David Lilienthal was known as \u201cMr\u201d this organization. Headquartered in Knoxville, for the point, name this New Deal organization that developed a series of dams in the South.", "answer": "<b> T.V.A</b> (or<b> Tennessee Valley Authority</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This thinker claimed that humanity is defined by its capability to begin new things, or its \u201cnatality.\u201dThis author of<em> The Concept of History</em> argued that creative work had been replaced as the center of life by futile labour in a work discussing the<em> vita activa</em>. This thinker described one form of government as \u201cradical evil\u201d and controversially compared Stalinism to Nazism. For the point, name this author of <em>The Human Condition</em> and<em> The Origins of Totalitarianism</em>, who described one Nazi\u2019s extremely average actions as the \u201cbanality of evil\u201d in<em> Eichmann in Jerusalem</em>.", "answer": "Hannah<b> Arendt</b> Page 3", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "This man, who was thought to be captured in Operation Le\u00b4a, held negotiations in a mud hut with champagne and ice. Huy Thuc wrote a song stating that this man is \u201cstill marching with us\u201d despite his death in 1969. At Versaillles, this man unsuccessfully presented an eight point plan to Woodrow Wilson for his country\u2019s self determination, and this leader told the French that they could kill \u201cten of my men,\u201dfor every one of theirs, but he would still win. For the point, name this victor of the Battle of Dien Bien Phu, a Vietnamese Communist after whom Saigon was renamed.", "answer": "<b> Ho</b> Chi Minh (or<b> Nguyen Sinh Cung</b> or<b> Nguyen Ai Quoc</b> or Bac<b> Ho</b> or<b> Nguyen Tat Thanh</b>, prompt on \u201cBac\u201d alone)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Great Peace of Montreal ended a Iroquois-Huron war fought for control of this resource. The York Factory was established at the mouth of the Hayes River to primarily trade this good. The Rocky Mountain Rendezvous was a massive annual meeting organized by traders and companies dealing in this commodity. John Jacob Astor founded a company to trade this good which eventually went bankrupt due to stiff competition from its Canadian rival. Hudson\u2019s Bay Company was founded to break the French monopoly on, for the point, what good often taken from beavers?", "answer": "<b> fur</b> (accept<b> hide</b>s; accept<b> beaver</b>s before it is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The final piece in the Vienna Philharmonic\u2019s New Year\u2019s Day program is a piece in this genre that commemorates the Battle of Custoza. Tchaikovsky wrote a piece in this genre for a benefit concert for wounded Serbians and was named for their ethnicity. Johann Strauss Sr. wrote a piece in this genre named for Count Radetsky, while other pieces in this genre include<em> The Liberty Bell</em>,<em> The Washington Post</em>, and <em>The Stars and Stripes Forever</em>. For the point, John Phillip Sousa was the \u201cking\u201d of what musical genre often depicting soldiers walking?", "answer": "<b> march</b>es Page 4", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Ross, Frank, and Florence Sterling founded a company in this state that sold one resource under the Enco and Humble brands and was based in Baytown. Patillo Higgins owned a company that struck black gold while speculating at Spindletop Hill near this state\u2019s city of Beaumont. This state was the main site of the deadliest natural disaster in American history, a 1900 hurricane that devastated Galveston, after which a nearby city on the Gulf Coast grew out of this state\u2019s oil boom. For the point, Hurricane Harvey interrupted oil refineries around what state\u2019s city of Houston.", "answer": "<b> Texas</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Julius Martov headed this party\u2019s main rival, which formed after this party split the RSDLP. That split was caused by this organizationss insistence on a strong core of professional revolutionaries, which was described in \u201cWhat is to be Done?\u201d This organization came to power in an event which toppled Alexander Kerensky\u2019s government. This political party, which seized power in the October Revolution, was misleadingly named \u201cthe larger party\u201d and was eventually renamed at the 19th Party Congress. For the point, what opponents of the Mensheviks was founded by Vladimir Lenin?", "answer": "The<b> Bolsheviks</b> (prompt on the Communist Party of the Soviet Union)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Donald Keene was renowned as a translator of works from this country.<em> Sora\u2019s Diary</em> is consulted as a reference text to a travel narrative from this country. The pleasure-seeking world of brothels and actresses in this country was depicted in its \u201cfloating world\u201d art, also known as<em> ukiyo-e</em>. Cutting words known as<em> kireji</em> and seasonal references called<em> kigo</em> are hallmarks of this country\u2019s 17-syllable poems. For the point, name this home country of Matsuo Basho whose authors invented the<em> haiku</em> form.", "answer": "<b> Japan</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "The Readjuster Party was a biracial coalition in this state that was destroyed by a 1902 poll tax. After the findings of the Perrow Commission, this state began a policy of \u201cpassive resistance\u201d to the desegregation of schools rather than the \u201cmassive resistance\u201d advocated for by Harry Byrd Sr. In 2019, this state\u2019s attorney general, Mark Herring, and its governor became embroiled in a blackface scandal. For the point, name this state governed by Ralph Northam from Richmond.", "answer": "<b> Virginia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This woman, the most prominent target of<em> libelles</em>, made an appeal during her trial to the mothers in the room while defending against the Dauphin, who was forced by Jacques H\u00b4ebert to accuse this woman of incest. During one affair, a prostitute was hired to impersonate this woman by Jeanne de la Motte. That affair sparked rumors that this woman and the Cardinal de Rohan were lovers and damaged this woman\u2019s reputation. For the point, name this target of the Diamond Necklace Affair and Queen of France who was guillotined during the French Revolution.", "answer": "<b> Marie Antoinette</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Martin McGuinness suggested a referendum in the aftermath of this event, in which the DUP refuses to consider a \u201cbackstop.\u201d Campaigning over this event was suspended for three days after Thomas Mair murdered MP Jo Cox for her opposition to this event. Nigel Farage resigned as the leader of UKIP after this event, which caused the downfall of David Cameron\u2019s government. Theresa May is currently charged with executing, for the point, what event following a 2016 referendum where Britain decided to leave the European Union?", "answer": "<b> Brexit</b> Page 7", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Erasmus wrote a dialogue that features this man trying to convince Peter to let him into heaven, threatening Peter with papal bulls and excommunication. The<em> Conciliabulum</em> of Pisa was opposed by this pope\u2019s calling of the Fifth Council of the Lateran. This pope allied with Louis XII of France and Emperor Maximilian I to fight against Venice in the War of the League of Cambrai. Buried near his uncle Pope Sixtus IV, this man rebuilt St. Peter\u2019s Basilica. For the point, name this member of the Della Rovere family, a \u201cWarrior Pope.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Julius II</b> the \u201cWarrior Pope\u201d or \u201cFearsome Pope\u201d (or<b> Giuliano della Rovere</b>) Page 8", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}